Guide to the Early Rice Institute records, 1844-1941 UA 101
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Early Rice Institute records
1844-1941
1880-1916
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Patrick, Albert T.; Baker, James Addison, 1930-; Rice, William Marsh, 1816-1900; Rice University
UA 101
62 Linear Feet
These records include the original William Marsh Rice murder trial records, and the estate records of Rice, founder of Rice Institute, now Rice University. These records relate to the formation of the idea of the Rice Institute and the activities of its first Board of Trustees in the years before Mr. Rice's death and to the Institute's formative years just after his death. The outcomes of the legal proceedings documented in these records, which related to significant financial resources and real estate, played the critical role in the creation of Rice Institute. A small amount of Rice's personal and business papers are also present.
(117 boxes)
62 lin. ft. (117 boxes)
Historical Sketch
William Marsh Rice was born in Springfield, Massachusetts on March 14, 1816. He was the third of ten children born to David and Patty Hall Rice. Little is known about Rice's childhood but records indicate that he worked for a while as a shopkeeper in Springfield before deciding to move to Texas in 1838.
Rice started out in business as a merchant in Houston, Texas. His first business partnership with a Barnabas Haskill was formed in 1840 but dissolved by 1842. In 1844 Rice became a commission and forwarding merchant in partnership with Ebenezer B. Nichols, a Houston businessman. By 1850 Rice's siblings began to follow him to Houston and assisted in his ventures. On June 29, 1850 Rice married Margaret Bremond whose father Paul was one of Rice's many business partners. In the census of 1860, Rice is listed as having $750,000 in real and personal property, making him one of the wealthiest men in Texas at the time.
At least 15 enslaved people were included as Rice's property in 1860. According to county deed records and newspaper advertisements, Rice purchased, sold, and accepted mortgages on enslaved people; he also attempted to recapture enslaved people who fled him. In addition to extending credit to slaveowners who leveraged enslaved people as collateral, Rice also bought and sold cotton as a substantial portion of his antebellum business. Rice served on a secession committee in Houston after the 1860 presidential election, and during the Civil War, Rice and his wife Margaret raised money for Confederate soldiers. On August 13, 1863, Margaret Rice died, possibly from cholera or yellow fever. Shortly after his wife's death, Rice went to Monterrey, Mexico and stayed there until August of 1865 when he returned to Houston. In Monterrey, Rice smuggled cotton and manufactured goods across the Texas-Mexico border. Later in the summer of 1865, he went to Massachusetts for business and did not return to Houston until 1866. On June 26, 1867 Rice married for a second time. His second wife was Julia Elizabeth Baldwin Brown, a widow and a daughter of Horace Baldwin, one of the early mayors of Houston. Elizabeth's sister Charlotte was the wife of William's younger brother Frederick.
Rice and his second wife moved to New Jersey to live with Rice's sister Charlotte and her family. Rice and his wife divided their time between New York City and New Jersey with occasional trips to Houston to oversee business. During one of the Rices' visits to Houston, he was approached by Cesar Maurice Lombardi, who was interested in building a high school in Houston. Rice had been interested in endowing an educational institute of some kind, having revised his will twice previously to include a school for needy boys, first in New Jersey, then in New York City. After the meeting with Lombardi, Rice decided to fund an institute of higher learning in Houston. On May 19, 1891 the charter for the William M. Rice Institute for the Advancement of Literature, Science and Art was incorporated in Austin, Texas. Captain James Addison Baker, William's brother Frederic, Houston businessmen Emanuel Raphael, Cesar Lombardi, James E. McAshan and Alfred S. Richardson were named as the first board of trustees.
In article two of the charter: "(t)he objects, intents, and purposes of this Institution are declared to be the establishment and maintenance, in the City of Houston, Texas, of a Public Library, and the maintenance of an Institution for the Advancement of Literature, Science, Art, Philosophy and Letters; the establishment and maintenance of a Polytechnic school; for procuring and maintaining scientific collections; collections of chemical and philosophical apparatus, mechanical and artistic models, drawings, pictures and statues; and for cultivating other means of instruction ..." The charter also required that the Institute only accept white students, which was changed in 1965. The institute was initially endowed with a promissory note for $200,000 to be paid upon Rice's death. Rice revised his will on September 26, 1896 and left the bulk of his estate to his namesake institute.
During the battle over the estate two lawyers became involved with the proceedings and would end up greatly influencing the final results. Captain Baker, a trustee of the Rice Institute, served as William Rice's lawyer. Albert Patrick, the other lawyer, was hired by Orren Holt in 1898 to investigate the residency question in New York City. There Patrick met Charlie Jones, Rice's valet. The two spent a great deal of time together and slowly a plan was formed. At first it seemed that Patrick was only interested in the settlement of the contested will and was looking for any way to win. He convinced Jones, in the spring of 1900, to start poisoning Rice with mercury pills as a way to avoid a court battle. By the summer of 1900 Patrick came up with the idea to forge a will that left the majority of Rice's estate to himself and small sums to relatives and friends. The forged will was dated June 30, 1900.
On September 8, 1900 a hurricane struck the Gulf Coast and one of Rice's businesses, the Merchants and Planters Oil Company, suffered severe damage. The business manager telegraphed that they needed money for repairs and the sum was most of what Rice had available in his bank account. Patrick was worried at the loss of such a large sum of ready cash and he convinced Jones to use chloroform to kill Rice. On September 23, 1900 Rice was murdered by Jones. Patrick, in his haste to get hold of Rice's cash, tried to withdraw money from Rice's bank using a check forged by Jones right after Rice's death. The bank refused to honor the check since Patrick's name was spelled incorrectly. When calling to verify the check with Rice, the bank learned that he was dead. Since the circumstances were suspicious, the bank contacted Rice's Houston lawyer, Captain Baker.
When Baker arrived in New York City, he learned there had been a new will written up by Patrick. Baker was suspicious of the will since Rice had never notified him of any changes to the one Baker had drawn up on September 26, 1896. This suspicion led to a long and sensational trial where Patrick's version of the will was exposed as a forgery and the scheme to kill Rice was discovered. Patrick was found guilty of murder and forgery on March 26, 1902 and was sentenced to die in the electric chair. Jones, who confessed to his part of the events, ended up being released despite being the one who had actually committed the murder. Patrick's sentence was commuted to life imprisonment by the governor of New York, but eventually won a full pardon in 1912.
On February 6, 1902 Orren Holt settled the suit over Elizabeth's will for $200,000. After the trials and settlement, Captain Baker and the original Board of Trustees set about fulfilling Rice's dream to have an institute for higher learning in Houston, Texas. To guide them, the trustees chose as first president, a young mathematician and astronomer at Princeton University named Edgar Odell Lovett, who signed on as president in 1908. Lovett had earned doctorates both from the Universities of Virginia and Leipzig and had taught at Johns Hopkins, the University of Chicago, and Princeton, the most innovative American universities of the time. The trustees sent him on a worldwide tour of the "competition," where he interviewed faculty, inspected facilities, and developed an inspired vision of what might be accomplished on the plains of Texas with a blank-check charter, a generous endowment, and high ambitions. The goal was a university "of the highest grade" that kept "the standards up and the numbers down." Lovett shaped the university that Rice would become.
The Rice Institute opened on September 23, 1912, the anniversary of Mr. Rice's murder, with 77 students and a dozen faculty. An international academic festival celebrated the opening three weeks later, a spectacular event that brought Rice to the attention of the entire scholarly world. Four years later, at the initial commencement, 35 bachelor degrees and one master's degree were awarded, with the first doctorate conferred in 1918.
Scope and Contents
These records include the original William Marsh Rice murder trial records, and the estate records of Rice, founder of Rice Institute, now Rice University. These records relate to the formation of the idea of the Rice Institute and the activities of its first Board of Trustees in the years before Mr. Rice's death and to the Institute's formative years just after his death. The outcomes of the legal proceedings documented in these records, which related to significant financial resources and real estate, played the critical role in the creation of Rice Institute. A small amount of Rice's personal and business papers are also present.
See Series descriptions in the Detailed Description of the Collection for more information.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 1-18 and 20-117 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. This material requires 24 hrs. for retrieval. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Boxes 19a-19b containing glass plates are located onsite at Woodson Research Center.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This material was a gift from the law firm Baker, Botts, Shepherd & Coates, and a transfer from within the university, 1962 and 1984.
Index Terms
Subjects
Slavery; Universities and colleges; Business; Courts
Document Types
financial records; corrrespondence; receipts (financial records); legal documents
Places
Texas -- Houston
- Series I: Court cases, 1886-1907 (Boxes 1-50), 241813
  Scope and Contents note
  These cases are filed chronologically based on each case's beginning date. Major cases include cases challenging William Marsh Rice's late wife's will and William Marsh Rice's murder trial. Each generally includes correspondence, notes, and legal documents such as testimony, exhibits, trial documents, affidavits, releases, published versions of the trials, and newsclippings.
  The first case is that of William Marsh Rice vs. Orren T. Holt, executor of Mrs. Elizabeth Baldwin Rice's estate, 1896-1902, regarding Rice's challenge to his wife's will. This trial began while W.M. Rice was living and continued after his death. Mrs. Rice's will assumed that the couple's property was divisible equally under Texas' community property law, and would have given away significant funds and lands, including the land on which Rice University sits today. W.M. Rice and his representatives proved that the couple were actually residents of new York and not Texas, making Mrs. Rice's will essentially null. The lawyer for Mrs. Rice's executor, Orren T. Holt, was Albert T. Patrick, who features as the defendant in the Rice murder trial. This case was settled in 1903 for $200,000.
  The second case is William Marsh Rice's murder trial, People of the State of NY vs. Patrick, 1900-1902. The evidence available here includes medical and handwriting experts' testimony, as well as the original glass plate negatives of Rice's real and alleged signatures used to prove Patrick's forgery of the 1900 Wm. M. Rice will, which benefited Patrick greatly and essentially scrapped significant plans for the Rice Institute, thereby proving Patrick's motive for the murder. Patrick was convicted and went to prison, but only a few years later was pardoned and released.
  Adele Baldwin vs. W. M. Rice Jr. & executors of Rice will, 1886-1908, the last large case in this series, relates to Mrs. Elizabeth Baldwin Rice's heirs challenging the executors of W.M. Rice's estate and is essentially a continuation of William Marsh Rice vs. Orren T. Holt. In November 1905, the case was decided, then appealed. Attorneys included Arthur Turnure of NY, for administrators of estate of E.B. Rice; William B. Hornblower, Atty. for estate of Wm. M. Rice (Hornblower, Byrne, Miller & Potter, of NY); and Oran Holt, Houston representative for E.B. Rice estate, with A.T. Patrick as his NY legal representative (up until the time of his trial and incarceration).
  - Subseries A: WMR vs. Orren T. Holt, executor of Mrs. Rice's will, 1894-1904 (Boxes 1-5), 242282
    - Elizabeth Baldwin Rice wills, 242310 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Statements by William Marsh Rice, 242309 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Statements by others, 242308 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1894-1899, 242307 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lands belonging to William M. Rice, 242306 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Notes, printed materials, 242305 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 339 Equity, Circuit Court of U.S., Eastern District of Texas at Galveston, 242304 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - No. 339 Equity, Circuit Court of U.S., Eastern District of Texas at Galveston, printed version: Depositions: William M. Rice vs. Oran T. Holt, Executor of the Last Will and Testament of Elizabeth B. Rice, deceased. Depositions of William M. Rice and others, on behalf of complainant taken August 1898, before Edward C. Manners, Special Examiner (copy certified by examiner)., 242303 (Box 2, Folder -)
    - Depositions: Alice Hanks Adams, Benjamin Perkins Bailey, Anna Baldwin, Edward Banks, John D. Bartine, Charles S. Benedict, C.W. Bocock, Lilla McDougall Boothby, George F. Brown, Charles Carpenter, Isabel H. Carpenter, Louise Clappe, John Cooper., 242302 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Depositions: Conrad Cramer, Henriette Cruger, Paul Bremond Cruger, Mary Harris Ewer, Clemente Fernandez, George N. Fischer, Blanchard Fosgate, Joseph Fourmy, Furman H. Gise, Mrs. Alexander S. Glassford, William A. Grant, Mary E. House, James H. Jenkins, Lizzie M. Lages, Sara J. Lippincott, David Lowrie, 242301 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Depositions: John Edward Matheson, Morris Meyers, Hannah C. Morris, Lalla Baldwin Morton, Laura Geddes Morton, Nadine Neftel, E. Raphael, Robert S. Reid, Paul Reusch, 242300 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Depositions: Juila D. Roberts, Mrs. Marion Robinson, William Garland Rucker, Walter G. Runyon, John Stafford, Mary E. Todd, Robert Kingsley Tomlin, Mary P. Trapp, Josephine Trust, Katie G. Trust, Mary E. Turnure, Maria Van Alstyne, 242299 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Depositions: Dr. Charles Warner, Ruth A. Watrous, Annie L. Winslow, 242298 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Draft of interrogatories re. E.B. Rice's rights, 242297 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Names of witnesses, arranged alphabetically, 242296 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Dates of hearings, persons present, witnesses examined, 242295 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Complainant's exhibits A-F, photographs of Rice property Dunellen, in New Jersey, photos dated November 6, 1899., 242294 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Transcripts in the record of No. 219 Equity of O.T. Holt, Executor vs. T.W. House et al, District Court of Washington County, Texas, June 6, 1898. Suit relates to disputed interests in various tracts of land. House is a co-defendant of William M. Rice., 242293 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Memorandum, No. 339 Equity, Rice vs. Holt. Summary of case, undated., 242292 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: James A. Baker Jr. to Spencer Hutchins, August 29, 1899 with enclosure to William M. Rice, August 29, 1899., 242291 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Collection of letters re. Elizabeth Baldwin Rice and her estate, and to and from A.T. Patrick and O.T. Holt, ca. 1896-1902, 242290 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - United States Circuit Court, Southern District of Texas at Houston, Holt vs. William Marsh Rice Institute, C.L. No. 27. Records of case proceedings with index, 1897-1903., 242289 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letter from Hutcheson, Campbell and Hutcheson to O.T. Holt regarding Rice estate case, May 15, 1901. This letter describes the essential strengths and weaknesses of Holt's case against W.M. Rice's estate and begins to set the groundwork for the eventual settlement., 242288 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Baldwin vs. Rice, summary, 1903, 242287 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Transcript regarding settlement of Rice vs. Holt, n.d., 242286 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Compromise settlement, March 9, 1904, 242285 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Affidavit of E. Raphael, Secretary, Rice Institute, Aug. 11, 1904, 242284 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Notes, n.d., 242283 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: People of the State of NY vs. Patrick (William Marsh Rice murder trial 1990-1902), 1894-1907 (Boxes 6-40), 241991
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume I Selection of jury, Jan. 20-22, 1902, 242281 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume II Testimony, Jan. 22-29, 1902, 242280 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume III Testimony, Jan. 30-Feb. 10, 1902, 242279 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume IV Testimony, Feb. 11-18, 1902, 242278 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume V Testimony, Feb. 19-27, 1902 [2 folders], 242277 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume VI Testimony, Feb. 28-March 10, 1902 [2 folders], 242276 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume VII Testimony, March 11-18, 1902 [2 folders], 242275 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - People of the State of New York vs. Albert T. Patrick: Volume VIII Testimony, March 19-April 4, 1902 [2 folders], 242274 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - Unidentified trial proceedings, 242273 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Abstracts of testimony (synopses), 242272 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Affidavits, Statements, 242271 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Statements regarding when people last saw WMR, 242270 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Abstracts of testimony (statements, synopses), 242269 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
    - Testimony (statements, synopses, examinations…) of individuals, 242150
      - Acheson, Harold S., 242268 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Adams, Charles T., 242267 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Alsdorf, Edward G., 242266 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Anderson, Robert C., 242265 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Aulich, Robert H., 242264 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Baker, James A. Jr., 242263 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Baldwin, Lillie, 242262 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Baldwin, William L., 242261 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Bartine, John D., 242260 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Bauer, Bessie, 242259 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Blinn, Frederick L., 242258 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Blinn, Joseph L., 242257 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Boothby, J.W., 242256 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Brightwell, James D., 242255 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Brown, William G., 242254 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Cahill, 242253 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Capron, Mary, 242252 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Cargill, Ennis, 242251 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Carpenter, Charles, 242250 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Childers, 242249 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Chilson, H.B., 242248 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Coff, Edward J., 242247 (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Cohn, Arthur B., 242246 (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - Coleman, J.M., 242245 (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - Costello, Elizabeth, 242244 (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - Dale, William, 242243 (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - Decker, Arthur, 242242 (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - Dunham, Curtis, 242241 (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - Ettinger, Louis, 242240 (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - Emory, John T., 242239 (Box 11, Folder 25)
      - Fane, John, 242238 (Box 11, Folder 26)
      - Findlay, Charles H., 242237 (Box 11, Folder 27)
      - Ford, Thomas W., 242236 (Box 11, Folder 28)
      - Francis, Addie M., 242235 (Box 11, Folder 29)
      - Gale, Lucy, 242234 (Box 11, Folder 30)
      - Gerard, James W., 242233 (Box 11, Folder 31)
      - Gould, Charles W. & son, 242232 (Box 11, Folder 32)
      - Graham, James J., 242231 (Box 11, Folder 33)
      - Grant, 242230 (Box 11, Folder 34)
      - Grotty, A. (alias "W. Bacon"), 242229 (Box 11, Folder 35)
      - Guile, Harry J., 242228 (Box 11, Folder 36)
      - Hamlin, George N., 242227 (Box 11, Folder 37)
      - Harby, Mark E., 242226 (Box 11, Folder 38)
      - Harmon, William F., 242225 (Box 11, Folder 39)
      - Hertford, William E., 242224 (Box 11, Folder 40)
      - Hervey, George, 242223 (Box 11, Folder 41)
      - Houlehan, John, 242222 (Box 11, Folder 42)
      - Jayne, 242221 (Box 11, Folder 43)
      - Johnson, F. Severance, 242220 (Box 11, Folder 44)
      - Jones, Charles F., 242219 (Box 11, Folder 45)
      - Jones, Charles F., statements and confession, 242218 (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
      - Jones, William Lafayette, 242217 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Kate, 242216 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Knowles, Andrew N., 242215 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Lansdale, 242214 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - LeDuc, Marie Clinton, 242213 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Long, William H., 242212 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Mallaby, Leonard B., 242211 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Manners, Edward C., 242210 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Marshall, Olive, 242209 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Matheson, J.A., 242208 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Mayer, Joseph D., 242207 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - McCarthy, Charles, 242206 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - McHugh, Annie, 242205 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Meldrum, N.S., 242204 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Melles, Dorothy, 242203 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Mellett, Lillian, 242202 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Meyers, Morris, 242201 (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
      - Mikanek, Charles, 242200 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Miller, Frank, 242199 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Moore, A.J.P., 242198 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Moore, J. Owen, 242197 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Moore, W.H., 242196 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Moran, John H., 242195 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - O'Keefe, John, 242194 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Oliver, Henry, 242193 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Palmer, Richard, 242192 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Pastoriza, Joseph J., 242191 (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Patrick, Albert T., 242190 (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Pedell, Joseph F., 242189 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - Peters, Curtis, 242188 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - Petznick, Leah, 242187 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - Plowright, Charles, 242186 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Potter, Mark W., 242185 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Potts, John R., 242184 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Pratt, James M., 242183 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Randolph, Andrew T., 242182 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Raphael, Emanuel, 242181 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Records, Edward, 242180 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Rice, Frederick A., 242179 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Rice, William M. Jr., 242178 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Rober, 242177 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Roeder, Gustav C., 242176 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Rucker, William G., 242175 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Schepflin, Christian, 242174 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Schmitt, George F., 242173 (Box 14, Folder 14)